Guide to the Joseph E. Holloway papers, 1980-1991
Holloway, Joseph E. papers, 1980-1991
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Joseph E. Holloway papers, 1980-1991
4511
Joseph E. Holloway
2.2 cubic ft., 13 videocassettes, 6 audiocassettes
Book manuscripts and drafts, correspondence, video and audiocassettes.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Mostly manuscripts and drafts of Holloway's books; and videotaped interviews of various Gullah and Oyotunji people. Includes correspondence and a copy of Holloway's dissertation.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
In 1983, Dr. Joseph Holloway received a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities to collect, interpret, and record "Africanisms" in American culture. He traveled extensively compiling this data, and in 1990, the University of Indiana, Bloomington published his findings in Africanisms in American Culture.
Holloway received additional funding from California State University, Northridge to conduct further research, including videotaped interviews with prominent persons in the field.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Original mss., typeset proofs, galley proofs, notes, and illustrations for Africanisms in American Culture; mss. and multiple drafts of essays published in that book, including: "The Origins of African-American Culture" by Holloway, "African Elements in African-American English" by Molefi Kete Asante, "Gullah Attitudes Toward Life and Death" by Margaret W. Creel, "Africanisms in African-American Music" by Portia K. Maultsby, and "The African Heritage of White America" by John E. Philips. Also mss. "Africanisms in Gullah Oral Tradition," published in Western Journal of Black Studies, 1989; mss. and mutiple drafts of African Heritage of American English (working title of "Dictionary of Africanisms", 1993, co-authored with Winifred K. Vass; and Holloway's UCLA dissertation, 1980, "Liberian Diplomacy in Africa: A Study of Inter-African Relations Between 1957 and 1966." Also thirteen videocassettes of interviews with various Gullah and Oyotunji people concerning culture, heritage, language and africanisms, and six audiocassettes of similar interviews.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Holloway, Joseph E. Liberian Dipolomacy in Africa.
Subjects:
African languages.; African Americans.; African Americans--Social life and customs.; Gullahs.; Sea Islands Creole dialect--South Carolina.
Places:
South Carolina--Social life and customs.; United States--Civilization--African influences.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence and Grant Application
Box 1
Series II. Writings
Boxes 1-9
Series III. Video and audio recordings
V-83 - V-95; TR-6752a - TR-6757a
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence and Grant Application
  - Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-June 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, July-Dec. 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Jan.-Mar. 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Apr.-May 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, June-Dec. 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - School of Social and Behavioral Sciences: Mini-grant application, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II. Writings
  - Africanisms in American Culture: Galley proofs (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Africanisms in American Culture: Front matter and introduction, typeset proofs (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Africanisms in American Culture: Introduction (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Africanisms in American Culture: Introduction/Review essay (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Africanisms in American Culture: African Elements in African-American English by Molefi Kete Asante (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Africanisms in American Culture: The African Heritage of White America by John E. Philips (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Africanisms in American Culture: Africanisms in African-American Music by Portia K. Maultsby (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Africanisms in American Culture: Gullah Attitudes Toward Life and Death by Margaret Washington Creel (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Africanisms in American Culture: The Origins of African-American Culture (Box 2, Folder 7-13)
  - Africanisms in American Culture: Illustrations and photographs used in the book (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Africanisms in American Culture: Illustrations and photographs not used (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Africanisms in Gullah Oral Tradition (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Various drafts (Box 3, Folder 1-10)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Various drafts (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Complete manuscript (Box 4, Folder 5-8)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Introduction (Box 4, Folder 9-12)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Introduction (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Introduction and bibliography (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Introduction, Chapters 1-2 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Introduction, Chapters 1 and 5 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Ch.1, Bantu Vocabulary Content of Gullah (Box 5, Folder 7-13)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Ch.1, Bantu Vocabulary Content of Gullah (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Chapters 1-4 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Ch. 2, Black Names in America (Box 6, Folder 3-8)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Ch. 3, Africanisms of Bantu Origins in Black English (Box 6, Folder 9-12)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Ch. 4, Bantu Place-Names in Nine Southern States (Box 6, Folder 13-14)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Ch. 5, Africanisms in American English (Box 6, Folder 15-17)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Ch. 5, Africanisms in American English (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
  - Dictionary of Africanisms: Miscellaneous notes (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
  - Liberian Diplomacy in Africa, thesis (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
  - Liberian Diplomacy in Africa, thesis (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - A Short of the West Indies (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Various student papers (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
- Series III. Video and Audio Recordings
  - Video Recordings
    - Interview with the Chief of Oyotunji, Sheldon, South Carolina, V-83
    - Interview with the Chief of Oyotunji, Sheldon, South Carolina, V-84
    - Oyotunji interviews: Chief Alagba on New World Africanisms, V-85
    - 7th Annual Penn School Heritage Celebration, African and Gullah, Nov.14, 1987, V-86
    - Africanisms and Gullah Culture; 7th Annual Celebration; Spirituals and Folklore, Nov.14, 1987, V-87
    - 8th Annual Heritage on Friday, Nov. 11, 1988, Part II, Folklore and Gospel music, V-88
    - Africanisms and Gullah Culture, 9th Annual Heritage Day Celebration, Nov. 9-11, 1989, V-89
    - Interview with Leroy Brown, first Black elected to office since Reconstruction; Interviw with Mr. Dan Watson on Gullah heritage, V-90
    - Interviews: Dan Watson on Gullah heritage, Rev. Ervin Greene on Africanism in the Gullah heritage, V-91
    - New Orleans (Kongo Square); Melrose Plantation; Africa House; U.S. Davis Wood Carver; Interview W.W. Law Bl. Ga., V-92
    - Africanisms - Coiled baskets (Gullah), Gravesites (slides on video), V-93
    - Interview with Claude and Pat Sharpe (linguist), Gullah translation of the Bible; Coffin point graveyard; Ron Daise oral history/folklore, V-94
    - Interview with Claude and Pat Sharpe; Gullah language and culture part II, V-95
  - Audio Recordings
    - Interview with Leroy Brown, Africanisms and Gullah history, TR-6752a
    - Interview with Leroy Brown and Dale Community Center/folklore, TR-6753a
    - Interview with Ruby Iyan, passing children over coffin, TR-6754a
    - Elizabeth Genn, Africanisms in the U.S., TR-6755a
    - Interview with Mrs. Elizabeth Genn (1983) root med./folklore, TR-6756a
    - Gullah folklore and customs, Gospel music, TR-6757a